Finding Aid for Jack Kevorkian papers, 1911-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
While in prison, Kevorkian continued to write. He prepared essays that accompanied art, music, photographs, books, and poetry, to be included in the exhibit, "The Doctor Is In: The Art of Dr. Jack Kevorkian," which opened in September 1999 at the Armenian Library and Museum of America in Watertown, Massachusetts. In April 2000 he received the Gleitsman Citizen Activist of the Year Award and a sculpture designed by Maya Lin, creator of the Vietnam War Memorial in Washington, D.C. In 2002 Kevorkian participated, through written questions, in a program on death and dying at Oklahoma City University. Also in 2002 Dr. Kevorkian was nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize. In August 2003 he was called to give deposition, as an expert witness on medical research on the effect of mercury on human tissue, based on his early writings on the subject. He prepared articles for The New York Times, the William Safire column, "On Language," Forbes ASAP, Popular Mechanics, New York Review of Books, The Nation, and American Journal of Forensics Psychiatry, among others. Kevorkian wrote the books glimmerIQs (2004)--an anthology on previous research and new material on philosophy, medicine, mathematics, religion, history, health, medicine, art, humor, his life, and the future; Amendment IX: Our Cornucopia of Rights (2005)--a book on the subject of the U.S. Bill of Rights; and in 2007 Kevorkian started working on Dear Dr. Jack, using selected letters out of the thousands written to him by supporters during his incarceration.
After eight years in prison, on June 1, 2007, Kevorkian was paroled for good behavior and released from the Lakeland Correctional Facility. He was on parole for two years, under the conditions that he not assist anyone else in dying or provide care for anyone older than 62 or disabled. He was also forbidden by the rules of his parole from commenting about assisted suicide. Kevorkian said he would abstain from assisting any more terminal patients with Medicide and that he would restrict his role to persuading states to change their laws on assisted suicide.
As Kevorkian was suffering from liver damage due to his advanced stages of Hepatitis C, doctors suspected he had little time left to live. However, in 2008, at the age of 79, Kevorkian decided to run as an Independent candidate for the U.S. Congress, against Republican Joe Knollenberg and Democrat Gary Peters. Also in 2008, he began working on his book, When the People Bubble Pops, about the dangers of overpopulation around the world. In 2009 Kevorkian lectured to more than 5,000 students--at the University of Florida, Wayne State University, and other colleges. The following year Kevorkian wrote on the subject of the Ninth Amendment in the form of a Bill of Rights of Natural Rights, prepared another anthology of his early research for World Press, and spoke to the Armenian Association at UCLA.
In 2010 Kevorkian attempted to travel to Armenia but was not allowed on the plane from Berlin, Germany. Also that year he met with the executive team of the HBO film, You Don't Know Jack. Production had begun in 2005, while Kevorkian was still imprisoned. The film is based in part on the book, Between the Dying and the Dead: Dr. Jack Kevorkian's Life and the Battle to Legalize Euthanasia by Neal Nicol and Harry Wylie (University of Wisconsin Press, 2006). The film featured Al Pacino as Jack Kevorkian, Brenda Vaccaro as Margaret Janus, Susan Sarandon as Janet Good (a longtime civil rights worker who cooperated with Kevorkian), Danny Huston as Geoffrey Fieger, and John Goodman as Neal Nicol. The film was released later in 2010 and was nominated for 16 Emmys. Kevorkian attended the 2010 Emmy Awards in Los Angeles, where Al Pacino asked him to "stand before the world." In addition to You Don't Know Jack, he was the subject of the documentaries Right to Exit (2004) and Kevorkian (2010).
Kevorkian's art has received critical acclaim. Many of his paintings created after 1993 are preserved in a permanent collection of Dr. Jack Kevorkian's materials at the Armenian Library and Museum of America in Watertown, Massachusetts. Kevorkian referred to his paintings as social, political, and medical commentaries that should provoke thought and discussion on aspects of life that may be disagreeable but are universal. Several of the paintings are part of a series on medical signs and symptoms, in which Kevorkian shows the conditions of human suffering that he witnessed on a daily basis.
His musical art depicts the lighter side of mankind. An active musician and composer, he played and composed pieces for flute, organ, piano, and keyboard. His personal idol was Johann Sebastian Bach, whose works were played in Kevorkian's hospital room before he died. Kevorkian's own musical compositions are strongly influenced by Bach, and some of his 1999 paintings are celebrations of Bach's music.
In 2010 Kevorkian's website, The Kevorkian Papers, was launched www.thekevorkianpapers.com.
Dr. Jack Kevorkian died on Friday, June 3, 2011, at William Beaumont Hospital in Royal Oak, Michigan. With him were his niece, Ava Janus, and his attorney and friend, Mayer Morganroth. Kevorkian was 83.
The Jack Kevorkian papers are arranged into five series: Kevorkian Family; Research and Practice, Morganroth & Morganroth; Personal Interests, and Medicide Files.
The Jack Kevorkian Papers are arranged into five series: Kevorkian Family, Research and Practice, Morganroth & Morganroth, Personal Interests, and Medicide Files.
The Kevorkian Family papers mostly include correspondence, recollections, photographs, and video and audio recordings of family gatherings. The Research and Practice series contains Kevorkian's correspondence on scientific subjects, his research files, and Kevorkian's articles on various medical, ethical, and bioethical topics. Also included are recorded interviews and media segments featuring Kevorkian as well as media reports about his activities and court trials. Materials in the Personal Interests series include sheet music of Kevorkian's musical compositions, recordings of Kevorkian playing music, reproductions of his paintings, publicity regarding exhibits of his art, and a sample of collected books. The Morganroth & Morganroth series includes materials used during the court trials, such as correspondence and Kevorkian's research as well as the script of the HBO film, You Don't Know Jack, annotated by Mayer Morganroth. The Medicide Files series contains the files of the terminally ill patients who had asked him assist in ending their lives and who he helped in doing so. Medicide files include correspondence between Kevorkian and his consulting "patients" and their families, photographs, and forms developed by Kevorkian as well as recordings of consultations.
Subjects:
Armenia.; Armenian Americans--Michigan.; Assisted suicide--Law and legislation--United States.; Assisted suicide--Moral and ethic aspects.; Constitutional amendments--United States.; Death row inmates.; Donation of organs, tissues, etc.; Euthanasia.; Kevorkian, Jack.; Kevorkian family.; Right to die.; Terminally ill.; Transplantation of organs, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Medical equipment & supplies.; Sick persons.
Contributors:
Morganroth, Mayer.
Genre Terms:
Digital file formats.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Paintings (visual works).; Photographs.; Placards (information artifacts).; Postcards.; Sheet music.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.; Websites.
- Kevorkian Family
  The Kevorkian Family series (1911-2014, 1 linear foot, oversize materials, and digital files) includes materials related to Jack Kevorkian's parents Lewis (Levon) and Satenig Kevorkian, his older sister, Margaret (Margo) Janus, and his niece, Ava Janus. Lewis Kevorkian's material includes his business ledgers, a small collection of business records, and various certificates and estate documentation. Satenig Kevorkian's papers include her letters, written in Armenian and dated between 1912 and 1919, as well as letters of condolence received by the family after her death. Margaret Janus's personal files include her correspondence, letters of condolence on her death, and obituaries as well as her diplomas, certificates, and collected personal effects. Ava Janus's materials include a small collection of correspondence and collected newspaper clippings on various subjects. Oversize Kevorkian family materials include collected articles on the 1915 Armenian genocide, passports, and maps. The Kevorkian family series includes photographs depicting family gatherings, snapshots, studio portraits, and wedding photos as well as a photo album of the Armenian Relief Corps of Pontiac, Michigan, dated 1930, that contains a photo of Satenig Kevorkian. The audiovisual materials include digitized video and audio recordings of family gatherings. Some audio recordings are partially in Armenian. There are also Jack Kevorkian portraits, photographs taken during his military service, and photos of his travels abroad.
  - Ava Janus, 1994-2012 (Box 1)
  - Flora Holzheimer (Kevorkian) (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - Lewis Kevorkian
    - Business ledgers, 1940-1943 1945-1960 (Box 1)
    - Business records, miscellaneous, 1923-1959 (Box 1)
    - Personal files, 1917-1960 (Box 1)
  - Margaret Janus
    - Biographical information, undated (Box 1)
    - Certificates and diplomas, 1943-1988 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (some correspondence is in Armenian and German)
    - Letters of condolence, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Notebooks and notes, 1959 undated (Box 1)
      (some in Armenian and German)
    - Personal files, 1936-1994 (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Satenig Kevorkian
    - Correspondence, 1912-1914, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
      (in Armenian)
    - Letters of condolence and obituaries, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Personal files, 1924-1963 (Box 1)
  - Oversize material related to Armenian history and the Armenian genocide of 1915, certificates of naturalization, oversize passports. (Box 9)
  - Audio recordings
    - Family Christmas, Margaret and Ava Janus, 1975 and 1987 Garden party, 1975, digitized audio cassette
      - [Side 1 of 1], [2014106-SR-1-1]; (Recording of unknown woman speaking on tradition and communicating to children. Tape sound is extremely distorted and difficult to hear.)
    - Family Christmas; Margaret and Ava Janus, 1975 and 1987; Garden party, 1987, digitized audio cassette
      - [Side 1 of 1], [2014106-SR-2-1]; (Miscellanous recordings of radio or television, children speaking into the tape, and other content.)
    - Recording of Margaret Janus and Satenig Kevorkian, circa 1975, digitized reel-to-reel audio
      - [Part 1], [2014106-SR-32-1]; (Beginning and end of tape contain recording of television broadcast playing in background. Recordings in Armenian from several family members on the ocassion of New Years.)
  - Films
    - Margaret Janus’ wedding, 1953, [2014106-16]; digitized 8 mm film; color; sil; 00:02:41; [Scenes from Margaret Janus' wedding in 1953. Recording is very dark.]
    - Untitled, undated, [2014106-17]; digitized 8 mm film; color; sil; 00:03:34; [Home recording of family trip in Europe(?) Depicts scenes of crowds and clergy(?) (No audio)]
    - Family event, undated, [2014106-1]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:02:34; [Home recording with scenes of family and children having dinner. "When you Wish Upon a Star" used as background music.]
  - Photographs
    (see also oversize)
    - 1911-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1922-1938 (Box 1)
      (with captions by Ava Janus)
    - 1922-1939
      (bl019100-bl019102)
    - 1930s-1970s, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1980s-1990s, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Jack Kevorkian (Box 1)
      - Certified Copy of Record of Birth, 1954
        (scanned images bl019103-bl019104)
      - 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
      - Military service, 1950s (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan, 1950s (Box 1)
      - Framed photograph of the University of Michigan Medical School Class of 1952 (Object 1)
      - Passport photos, 1990 undated, 3 photographs
        (bl019105-bl019108)
    - Lewis and Satenig Kevorkian (Box 1)
    - Other family members (Box 1)
    - Oversize photo album of the Armenian Relief Corps of Pontiac, Mich., 1930 (picture of Satenig Kevorkian on page 139), family photographs and a 1918 group photo at a funeral in Pontiac, Mich. (Box 9)
- Research and Practice
  The Research and Practice series (1928-2011, 3.3 linear feet, oversize items, digital files, and archived website) includes writings by Kevorkian and annotated research articles as well as his correspondence on various medical, ethical, and bioethical topics, specifically organ transplantation and the death penalty. Correspondence contains Kevorkian's exchanges with medical professionals, politicians, publishers, and his supporters on the subjects of organ transplantation, terminally ill patients' rights and the Ninth Amendment of the Constitution, Medicide, death-row prisoners' right to die by euthanasia, and "prisoner procurement" (voluntary donation of organs by death-row prisoners). There are letters addressed to Kevorkian, supporting or disagreeing with his theories and methods. Correspondence is organized chronologically, except for one folder that contains Kevorkian's Armenian-language correspondence with Armenian scientists. Also found here are topical files on several subjects. The "Euthanasia" topical file contains articles that have been annotated by Kevorkian. The "Prisoner procurement" files include letters and petitions by prisoners on death-row who wanted their organs donated after being executed by euthanasia. More on the discussion of auctioning human organs and making them available for sale is found across the series, in correspondence, in Kevorkian's written work, and in a folder titled "Viscus global auction."
  The series contains Kevorkian's published articles, monographs, and manuscript drafts. Folders with articles are arranged by decade; each contains a list of all articles published in the corresponding decade prepared by Ava Janus. Also found in this series is a folder containing material about the odontological dental retractor, a dental instrument that was invented by Kevorkian while he was imprisoned. The "Imprisonment" folder contains documents pertaining to his arrests, life in prison, parole hearings, and conditions of his parole.
  Also found here are biographical sketches, published biographies and essays about Kevorkian, clippings of newspaper articles about him, his curriculum vitae, certificates, awards, diplomas, images of Dr. Kevorkian's paintings and information about his art, sheet music, and a small collection of his personal correspondence.
  Photographs include images of Margaret and Ava Janus and Kevorkian's attorney, Geoffrey Fieger, as well as photographs of his medical instruments and personal effects. Digitized video recordings include compilations of recorded local news reports about Kevorkian as well as several special programs about his legal trial and about his work, aired on national television networks (e.g., Court TV, Frontline, 60 Minutes). Digitized audio recordings include his radio interviews (some given together with Fieger and others), recordings of his music, and music dedicated to him by others.
  This series also includes Kevorkian's professional diplomas, certificates, and contents of the archived website, "The Kevorkian Papers." There is a framed portrait of Kevorkian, called "Dr. Life" by Rachel Reed, created in 1993. The portrait bears the inscription, "Go on because you know you are right." This portrait was used by Kevorkian's supporters during public events.
  - Biographical information1928-2011 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Biographies and other works about Kevorkian
    - Appointment with Dr. Death by Michael Betzold (Troy, MI: Betzold, 1993) (Box 2)
    - Assisted Suicide: Based on the Case of Dr. Jack Kevorkian by Sevan Kalaydjian, 2008 (Box 2)
      (senior term project paper)
    - Dr. Death: Dr. Jack Kevorkian's Rx: Death by Joan Brovins and Thomas Oehmke (Hollywood, Fl.: Lifetime Books, 1993) (Box 2)
    - God Bless You, Dr. Kevorkian by Kurt Vonnegut (New York: Seven Stories Press, 1999) (Box 2)
    - Mavericks of Medicine: Conversations on the Frontiers of Medical Research interviews by David Jay Brown (Petaluma, CA: SmartPublications, 2006) (Box 2)
    - Murder or Mercy: Dr. Death: Dr. Jack Kevorkian's Rx: Death by Joan Brovins and Thomas Oehmke (advance uncorrected copy) (Box 2)
    - You Don't Know Jack: Between the Dying and the Dead by Neal Nicol and Harry Wylie (New York: World Audience, 2011) (Box 2)
    - You Don't Know Jack (Box 2)
      (material related to the 2010 HBO movie)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1950s-2014, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Certificates and diplomas
    - 1946-1981 undated (Box 2)
    - Certificates and diplomas (Box 9)
  - Check-Up Medical Diagnostic Center, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    (see also Morganroth & Morganroth series)
    - Undated (Box 3)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1982-2011, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - In Armenian, 1988, 1998 undated (Box 3)
  - Euthanasia subject file, 1981-1998 (Box 3)
  - Imprisonment, 1996-2011 (Box 3)
  - Lectures, 2007-2011, (includes correspondence, invitations, etc.) (Box 3)
  - Ninth Amendment subject file, 1994-2001 (Box 3)
  - Odontological Dental Retractor, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1960s-2010s undated, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated
    - Check-Up Diagnostic Laboratory Building in Southfield, Mich.
      (bl019111-bl019112)
    - Internal mechanism of the Medicide machine
      (bl019109-bl019110)
  - Prisoner procurement (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1984, 1987, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Prisoners' letters and petitions, 1984, 1995 undated (Box 3)
  - Research Medicide folder and drafts, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Viscus global auction, 1986-2002 (Box 3)
  - Website
    - The Kevorkian Papers website
    - Related materials, 2009-2010 (Box 3)
  - Writings
    (see also drafts in Morganroth & Morganroth series)
    - Articles, published, 1950s-2000s undated, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Articles, unpublished, 1988 undated (Box 4)
    - Books by Dr. Kevorkian (Box 4)
      (list of titles)
    - Limericks, undated (Box 4)
    - Manuscript drafts, undated (Box 4)
    - Monographs
      - Amendment IX (Bloomfield Hills, MI: Penumbra, 2005) (Box 4)
      - Amendment IX: Our Cornucopia of Rights (Bloomfield Hills, MI: Penumbra, date of publication not identified) (Box 4)
      - Beyond Any Kind of God (New York: Philosophical Library, 1966) (Box 4)
      - Finis (place of publication and publisher are not identified, 1974 ?) (Box 4)
      - Glimmeriks (Southfield, MI: Penumbra, 1979) (Box 4)
      - GlimmerIQs a Florilegium (Bloomfield Hills, MI: Penumbra, 2004) (Box 4)
      - GlimmerIQs a Florilegium (Bloomfield Hills, MI: Penumbra, 2009) (Box 4)
        (2 copies: paperback and hard cover)
      - Medical Research and the Death Penalty (New York: Vantage Press, 1960) (Box 5)
        (includes a book review)
      - Prescription: Medicide: the Goodness of Planned Death (Buffalo, NY: Prometheus Books, 1991) (Box 5)
      - Slimmeriks and the Demi-Diet (Bloomfield Hills, MI: Penumbra, 1978) (Box 5)
      - Story of Dissection (New York: Philosophical Library, 1959) (Box 5)
      - When the People Bubble Pops (New York: World Audience, 2010) (Box 5)
    - Speeches, 1970, 1973, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Posters, 2008 (Box 9)
  - Framed portrait "Dr. Life" by Rachel Reed, 1993 (Object 2)
  - Video recordings of Telvision News and Broadcast Programs, 1993-1995 2009-2010
    compilations of recorded local news segments from the Detroit area stations; nationally broadcasted TV programs 60 Minutes, Eyewitness News, interview on Fox News, Court TV, Frontline; and footage of June 4, 1994 Kevorkian's petition event in Midland, Mich, 360° with Anderson Cooper, Live with Larry King, The Cavuto Reports; interviews with Al Pacino, and recording of the 2010 Emmy Awards with footage of Kevorkian.
    - Channel 7 News from Dinner at Kipley Inn 1993 July 17, [2014106-2]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:09:03; [News story on dinner event where families have dinner with Dr. Kevorkian.]
      [BHL Reading Room Access Only]
    - Editorial Reply on Channel 7 1993 August 30, [2014106-3]; digitized VHS videotape; 01:07:35; [Margo Janus featured in an Editorial Reply on Channel 7.]
    - Editorial Reply on Channel 7 1993 August 31, [2014106-4]; digitized VHS videotape; 01:01:51; [News coverage on Dr. Kevorkian on trial, including Editorial Reply on Channel 7; Face to Face; Fox News; Channel 7 Action News; Channel 2 Eyewitness Morning; Eyewitness News; Channel 7 Action News, and Channel 2 Upfront; among others.]
    - News shows, NOW, Frontline and Larry King Live 1994 January 12, [2014106-5]; digitized VHS videotape; 01:53:45; [News coverage on Dr. Kevorkian and his work in NOW, Frontline and Larry King Live.]
    - Trial Story on Court TV 1994 May 02, [2014106-6]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:50:23; [News coverage on Dr. Kevorkian on trial in Trial Story.]
    - Dr. Kevorkian visits Midland 1994 June 04, [2014106-7]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:15:11; [Dr. Kevorkian visits Midland, Mich. where supporters rally in his favor.]
    - 60 Minutes episode on the topic of assisted suicide 1994 September 11, [2014106-8]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:15:28; [60 Minutes episode on the topic of physician assisted suicide.]
    - Frontline: The Kevorkian File 1994 December 20, [2014106-9]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:58:05; [Frontline episode with Dr. Kevorkian and Margo Janus.]
    - Margo Janus Mercy Clinic news coverage 1995, [2014106-10]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:27:26; [News coverage on the Margo Janus Mercy Clinic by Headline News, Eyewitness News, UPN 50 News, Channel 7 Action News, Channel 4 news, CNN Newsnight.]
    - Jack Kevorkian and Margo Janus; Larry King Live; ER 1995 February 02, [2014106-11]; digitized VHS videotape; 01:30:43; [Jack Kevorkian and Margo Janus practice using a video camera; Larry King Live; ER episode discussing physician assisted suicide.]
    - Headline News footage featuring Dr. Kevorkian (1995); other popular television shows 1995 August 30, [2014106-12]; digitized VHS videotape; 01:51:59; [Laurel and Hardy's Picture Perfect; Headline News featuring Dr. Kevorkian (1995), I Love Lucy episodes.]
    - Local and national news coverage on Jack Kevorkian and HBO film You Don't Know Jack 2009-2010, [2014106-13]; digitized VHS videotape; 04:29:00; [Compilations of recorded local news segments from the Detroit area stations as well as nationally broadcasted TV programs on Jack Kevorkian and HBO film You Don't Know Jack. Broadcasts include Fox 2 interview with Jack Kevorkian; Larry King Live; 360º with Anderson Cooper; TMZ; Seinfield.]
    - Fox News' Your World with Neil Cavuto 2010 April 19, [2014106-14]; digitized VHS videotape; 00:17:04; [Fox News' Your World with Neil Cavuto. Includes interview with Jack Kevorkian and discussion about HBO movie You Don't Know Jack.]
    - Recording of the 2010 Emmy Awards with footage of HBO film about Jack Kevorkian, You Don't Know Jack. 2010 August 29, [2014106-15]; digitized VHS videotape; 03:49:00; [Recording of the 2010 Emmy Awards with footage of HBO film about Jack Kevorkian, You Don't Know Jack.]
  - Audio recordings
    - Basically Business interview, undated, digitized audio cassette
      - [Side 1 of 1], [2014106-SR-3-1]; (Dr. Kevorkian on the Basically Business radio program discussing his assistive suicide equipment and its ethics.)
    - Dr. Jack Enhanced, undated, digitized audio cassette
      - [Side 1 of 1], [2014106-SR-6-1]; (Recording of organ music, no other content.)
    - I need Dr. Jack by Josh Weinstein, 1996, digitized audio cassette